If you're considering a move to central
Texas, two cities that almost always
make the short list are Temple and
Belton. Both are situated right along
the I35 corridor between Austin and
Waco, but they have some pretty big
differences in terms of lifestyles and
advantages. Temple, Texas is the larger
of the two, known more for its medical
and retail hub, anchored by Baylor Scott
and White Medical Center and its growing
list of employers. Belton is the smaller
of the two, known for its charming
historic downtown, Lake Belton, and
highly rated school district. But how do
the two compare when it comes to home
prices, property taxes, schools,
infrastructure, and overall living?
Well, that's exactly what we're taking a
look at today.
Hi, I'm Andrea Dudik and welcome back to
Living in Central Texas. Let's take a
closer look at Temple versus Dustin.
In Temple, you're generally going to
have a larger housing inventory, a lot
more established communities, as well as
new builds and overall communities. This
town is just a lot bigger. The homes
there are generally going to be more
affordable. A lot of this has to do with
property taxes and overall
desiraability. you're generally going to
get more value dollar per dollar. While
even still in this market, you're in a
buyer market. So, you're really going to
get a great value in either Temple or
Belton. Belton is a smaller market.
There's higher demand and slightly
higher home prices. So, if you were to
compare inventory in terms of size, that
being square footage, bed, bath, lot
size, and overall features, typically
it's going to be less expensive in
Temple, so um lower cost per square
foot. Of course, Belton has, you know,
premium pricing, which is going to be
tied to the community reputation, feel
higher property taxes and overall
demand. In general, in Bell County,
property taxes are going to range from
1.7 to 2.9, depending on a variety of
factors, including just where you are.
If you're inside of city limits, outside
of city limits, and honestly, Temple and
Belton are going to be pretty
comparable. Belton being slightly higher
in most areas. Um, as you hit Celo, so
Celo, Texas is going to fall generally
below a 2% property taxes. Some of the
outskirts of Belton as well. And then as
you head more north and Troy and some of
the outer areas, you're going to have
those lower property taxes, which can
make a big difference in your monthly
mortgage payments. Okay, so I wanted to
give you some really, really helpful
information and you started your home
search. So let's just say you're trying
to identify estimated property taxes. Of
course, you can always call me and we
can have a conversation. But if you want
to do a little research of your own, you
can head on over here to bellcad.org,
go to property search,
and then search right here by address.
And so, say you see a house on Zillow or
Realtor or wherever is you're searching.
Um, most of the time home phones will
come up on here unless someone has the
home ex um, protected like I think law
enforcement things of that nature. They
can put in a request so that this
information is private but majority of
the time houses will pop up in here as
they fall within Bell County. Or if
there's another county like Corel or
something, you can search that appraisal
district. But for now, we're going to
look at two. We're going to look at I
pulled a house and it sells for sale and
a house in Temple. That's for sale. So,
we're going to say 6004
Palamonte.
Okay, here it is. And this is public
information.
Now, Texas is a non-disclosure state.
Um, it's a little complicated, but
basically
the appraisal district does not need to
know or does not have public access to
what you actually paid for your home or
what someone paid for their home. So,
they use whatever metric they use. I
don't even know how they calculate that,
but they give an assessed value. So, for
this home, they're saying the assessed
value is about 356.
Here we are. 6004 pelamonte.
And if you scroll down here,
you can see all of the taxing
jurisdictions here.
And down here you have the 2024 total
tax rate as well as the annual base
taxes.
So 2.33 tax rate.
You can also call the calculator which
gives to you
to get a decent idea.
So, let's just say you have a $356,000
home times 2.34%.
There you go. Pretty close. 8,300
property taxes. So, as long as you know
what that tax rate is for that area, you
can get a pretty good estimate of how
much your annual property taxes are for.
So, this one was in
Temple. We're going to do another search
of one in Belton.
So, I did by address. You're going to do
Benton. And please remember that this
isn't across the board for Temple or
Belton that they do vary even per street
and per area. Now, this person does have
a homestead exemption. That's a whole
another video on this topic on
exemptions, but their taxes are going to
look different because they have that
exemption. But their assessed value is
372,
tax rate 2.27,
annual taxes about 7,469.
So little helpful tool if you want to go
ahead and and you ever need to check
that out. Utilities are roughly equal.
Uh, one of the biggest things that we
talk about, I was just speaking with
some out ofstate buyers as we were
looking at homes and they were like,
"Why isn't there gas?" Well, there's
just not. A lot of this area is electric
cooking, um, electric utilities, and so
you do get some gas. There is some
natural gas and some propane in some
areas, but more common is going to be
electric. Costs overall are going to be
pretty similar in terms of utilities.
Now, Temple and Belton both fall within
Bell County. And while there are a lot
of other cities that make up Bell
County, Temple and Belton are two of the
larger, more well-known cities in that
county. Temple has a population of just
over 80,000, while Belton has a
population of over 20,000. They're just
minutes apart from each other, and many
people will live in one city and work in
the other and just make a commute
because the commute is so small. Key
differences really come down to schools,
property taxes, and overall vibe. Now,
Temple is larger, so it's going to have
more housing options. It's also going to
have more affordable home prices. A part
of this is property taxes, and a part of
this is desiraability. You're going to
have a lot more variety as well. There
are a lot of more established homes in
this area, especially being in and
around the medical centers. I always
laugh when I first moved here. I
remember going over Lake Belton. It was
over 10 years ago. And my husband said,
"Um, yeah, that's our lake." And I said,
"Oh, what's it called?" And he said,
"Like Belton."
Okay. And then he looked at me kind of
crazy. And then he said, "That's the
high school I went to." And I said,
"What's it called?" And he said, "Belton
High School." And I just had to laugh
because being from Las Vegas, um it
wasn't there is a lake Las Vegas, but
the lake was called Lake Me. There were
dozens of high schools, so everything is
just a little bit different here. And I
love it. The charm is just so fantastic.
But Belton is growing. Their um Belton
ISD is a top rated school district. It
has an A rating. They have Lake Belton
High School which opened up in 2020 and
things are just expanding but in a very
I feel healthy way. It never really
feels congested to me here. Traffic is
overall going to be pretty minimal. I
honestly think that the school district
is one of the biggest driving factors
for Belton. Temple ISD has a larger more
diverse school district um in some of
the areas lower ratings. You can head on
over to niche.com and check out both
Temple ISD and Belton ISD if you would
like more information on the school
districts, but they both have very
different things to offer. Um, Temple
ISD has the STEM Academy. It's a
nationally recognized magnet program.
I'd also say Temple ISD has a lot of
diversity, innovation, and strong
specialty program. But if the school
district is something that's extra
important to you, always check the
boundaries. I've stress I've stressed
this time and time again. A lot of
Temple, Texas falls in Belton ISD. And
so if you would like more clarification
on that, you can always reach out to me
and I can help clarify for you. So if
you'd like to know more about either of
these school districts, you can head on
over to tisd.org
or bisd.org.
You'll find really great information
about them, district maps,
schoolboard, campuses, annual report,
and then you can also go to bisd.net,
find out all about enrollment
again, departments, more about that
school district. And then if you go to
niche.com
and up here at the top you can find a
school specifically. What I did is I
just went ahead and searched in Bel
County and these are all the homes that
fall within Bell County.
So like Lakewood is a really popular
one. Number two best public elementary
school in Bell County. But a lot of
really great resource information there.
If you are looking to buy in Temple or
Belton and Belton ISD, the school
district is the priority to you, do not
fall into the trap of only searching
Belton ISD because there is so much
overlap in City of Temple and there
being a lot of homes that are in Belton
ISD. I'm going to give you an example.
So, this is the MLS MLS. This is the
multiple listing service where we as
agents enter new listings and your sites
like Villow, Trullia, Realtor, Redfin,
they all pull information from the MLS.
So, this is the accurate source. So, if
I just run a search on here for Belton
ISD,
there are 584
541 active homes for sale.
And if I search by city,
there are a ton in Belton,
but there are also a ton in Temple. If
we look at the map,
when you zoom in,
here you have Temple
and here you have Felton.
that you can see that there are a lot of
homes
along the south and
west of Temple. So, it's really
important to do your research. If you
have a realtor, it's extra helpful.
And yeah, some really good information
there. What I don't think a lot of
people realize is that we are one of the
largest medical hubs between Austin and
Dallas, Texas.
We're a huge teaching facility that is a
huge driving force to the area as well
as the VA hospital, the University of
Mary Harden Baylor right in Belton and
our proximity to Fort Hood in Colleen,
Texas. Um that's just 25 minutes away.
So we get a ton of people relocating
here for military. Some other major
employers are um of course the VA MLAN
distribution center, the HB
distribution. Those are all within
Temple, Wilson Art Manufacturing Firm,
Engineering Services based in Temple,
Walmart distribution center, and we have
a ton of shopping and dining. And don't
forget, you're only 45 minutes away from
Waco, Texas, or an hour away from
Austin, Texas if you're looking for a
larger city feel. Belton, Texas has the
historic courthouse and square. I did a
full video on exploring downtown Belton
if you'd like a closer look at Belton,
but it's just so cute, so quaint, and
they've done so much to it even since
I've been here in the last decade. Some
of the local favorites are going to be
Cochran Blair and Pots, the gin, the gin
at Nolan Creek. It's so cute. You can
sit up over the creek and watch kids
play in the water during the summer.
It's just a really pretty peaceful view
and walk the square and experience some
of the awesome shopping and dining it
has to offer. The University of Mary
Hart and Baylor is right there in Belton
right off of the square. It adds a very
unique college feel and a big again big
driving force to the Belton area. Belton
has a strong manufacturing presence. its
firms producing metal goods, machinery,
manufactured homes, and more. The
takeaways, um, typically Temple is going
to be more of convenience, employment,
and access, maybe even affordability if
you still want the quick access to
Belton. And then Belton has more of that
lifestyle, charm, and nature. Belton is
really growthdriven by people looking to
be part of Belton ISD and that lake
living. I think one of its stronger
challenges is going to be maintaining
that small town feel as it continues to
expand. Right now, it definitely still
does. Temple's growth is centered around
jobs, infrastructure, and redevelopment.
If we're going to do a vibe check and a
little vibe comparison, Temple really
feels like the city that works. It's
busy. It's practical. It's diverse. And
Belton is just a town that lives. It's
connected, charming, and family
oriented. So, after all that data
comparison, where does that leave us?
The choice between Temple and Belton
isn't about one being objectively better
than the other. It's about which one
fits your situation, lifestyle, and
overall desires better. The beautiful
thing is you really can't make a bad
decision. Both Temple and Belton are
beautiful cities thriving in the heart
of central Texas. And if you live in the
Temple Belton area, I'd love to hear
from you. Leave a comment below and let
us know what you love most about living
in Temple Belton. And if you found this
video helpful, don't forget to like,
subscribe, and click the bell
notification so that you can stay
uptodate on all things real estate here
in Central Texas. Till next time.